<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-09-04T11:11:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">What is time?</title><subtitle>I seek to uncover the ontology of time. I seek to derive time, not define it. I seek to escape relativism!</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Opening Pandora’s box.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/02/Opening-pandoras-box.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Opening Pandora's box." /><published>2018-09-02T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-02T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2018/09/02/Opening-pandoras-box</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2018/09/02/Opening-pandoras-box.html">&lt;p&gt;There is a bug in the metaphysics of scientific reasoning and it’s caused by the very nature of human experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask a physicist if time is a scalar or a vector and they will tell you that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Problem_of_time&quot;&gt;it’s both&lt;/a&gt;. Huh? From which &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frame_of_reference&quot;&gt;reference frame&lt;/a&gt;? “Well it depends on how you define it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop right there! Science is not in the business of arbitrarily defining things.
Science is in the business of quantifying things in respect to other things, so what is time quantified in respect to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different starting assumption on the meaning of a symbol is by definition a different reference frame - a different perspective. And yet science prides itself on the notion of “objectivity”. That things are true irrespective of whether we believe them or not. The universe is the way it is - not the way we want it to be. It owes us no explanation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists always leave out the fine print. Things are true IF you accept and &lt;strong&gt;interpret&lt;/strong&gt; results against some fundamental axioms. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SI_base_unit&quot;&gt;seven base SI units&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK. Can you present me with a convincing argument as to why I should accept the SI units without appealing to pragmatism? As Dawkins said “Science works. Bitches”. I don’t dispute that science works. I am simply wondering if we can make it work even better if we were to align our units to the ontology of the universe. Also, what do you mean by “works”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science makes accurate predictions. And the momment I uttered this phrase my brain mis-fired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear scienctific method: You are guilty of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Performative_contradiction&quot;&gt;performative contradiction&lt;/a&gt;. You are comitted to a definition of time by the very meaning of the English word “prediction”! Given a deterministic information source I (subject/experiment) a prediction is a correct guess of a FUTURE observation/measurement of I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time(0) is The Big Bang, so how do we define the word “future”: I(time+N). N of WHAT ?!? What is time grounded in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbol_grounding_problem&quot;&gt;symbol-grounding problem&lt;/a&gt; breaks all of our languages and Mathematics is not immune to this bug!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SI &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SI_base_unit&quot;&gt;defines the second&lt;/a&gt; in relation to the cesium atom.
Did cesium atoms exist at t(1), or t(10) after the Big Bang? At the other end of the spectrum - does time continue to exist after the heat death of the universe and beyond maximum entropy?
Is spacetime infinite even though quantum physicists &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renormalization&quot;&gt;hate infinities&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t like any of the answers modern physics is giving me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I asked the question: What is time and what fundamental unit would I drrive it from? I don’t know. Yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My instincts (biases?) lead me towards &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entropy_(information_theory)&quot;&gt;Shannon entropy&lt;/a&gt; only because I grok it, but maybe the right answer hides in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Von_Neumann_entropy&quot;&gt;Von Neumann&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entropy_(statistical_thermodynamics)#Gibbs_entropy_formula&quot;&gt;Gibbs&lt;/a&gt; entropy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am less interested in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entropy_(arrow_of_time)&quot;&gt;Boltzmann entropy&lt;/a&gt; because it has pre-supposed time as a vector.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There is a bug in the metaphysics of scientific reasoning and it’s caused by the very nature of human experience.</summary></entry></feed>